Parker Family-Fort Parker collection, Inclusive: 1823-1983, undated, Bulk: 1959-1967, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Parker Family-Fort Parker collection
Inclusive: 1823-1983, undated, Bulk: 1959-1967, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2581
Connally, Ernest Lackey
2 document boxes.
The Parker Family-Fort Parker collection consists of manuscripts generated and collected by Ernest Connally for his research on Fort Parker and the Parker Family. The collection contains correspondence, legal documents, literary productions, photographic materials, and artifacts.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Ernest Connally was a citizen of Groesbeck, Texas, by 1936. It is possible that he was a member of the politically influential Connally family of Central Texas. In the 1930s, Connally was the president of the Fort Parker Association, the organization responsible for planning the centennial celebration for the fort. E.L. Connally, as he was popularly referred to, operated the Connally Funeral Home in Groesbeck, Texas, which is still in business as of 2011. Connally was active in many historic site projects in Central Texas, but he is most identified with Old Fort Parker. This collection reflects his interest in that park, primarily centering around the Parker family.
The Parker family came to Texas from Illinois in 1833, and settled north of Groesbeck in 1835. The small group built a fort for defense in case of Indian attacks, and concentrated on farming. On 1836 May 19 the fort was attacked by an Indian force of several hundred warriors, long understood by eyewitnesses to be Comanche Indians. Several Parker family members were killed and others were captured, but many escaped.
The few who were captured endured the loss of everything they knew. Different captives had different experiences. Eventually all of the captives were released and went back to their family in Texan society, but one girl, Cynthia Ann Parker, remained behind.
Cynthia Ann Parker, just twelve or thirteen when taken captive, was adopted into the tribe and became thoroughly Comanche. She married warrior Peta Nocona, who might have taken part in the attack on the Parker’s fort. Cynthia and Peta had three children together, two boys and a girl, Quanah, Pecos, and Topsannah. Peta Nocona was possibly killed in the Battle of the Pease River in 1860. Cynthia Ann was recaptured by Texas Rangers in this battle, and was identified as the Parker’s Cynthia Ann, who had been with the Comanche for almost twenty-five years. Though she was returned to Texan society, Cynthia Ann never recovered from her capture and made several attempts to escape back to her life on the plains. She died in 1870, widely understood to have passed away from a broken heart. She was buried in Fosterville Cemetery, Anderson County, but was reinterred in the Post Oak Mission Cemetery near Cache, Oklahoma, in 1910. Cynthia Ann was reburied a final time in 1957 in the Fort Sill Post Cemetery, Lawton, Oklahoma.
Cynthia Ann’s son Quanah Parker, not captured at the Battle of the Pease River, became the last major Comanche chief to surrender to United States authorities. A warrior in the Quahada subtribe of the Comanche, Quanah surrendered with what remained of his people in 1875. He adjusted to reservation life easily, and became a very wealthy man considering the circumstances he and his people were in. Though increasingly powerful in Indian-government relations, he could not stop the movement to break up the reservations and distribute the land among the individual Indians, who were then forced to sell much of their land by unscrupulous land dealers. Quanah continued his efforts to help his people however he could. After a visit to the Cheyenne Reservation, Quanah became ill and died twelve days later, in 1911. His remains have been moved once, from Post Oak Mission Cemetery in Oklahoma to Fort Sill Post Cemetery, Lawton, Oklahoma.
The fort the Parkers built in 1835 was destroyed by the Indian raiding party. In the 1930s, the site was selected as a work area for the Civilian Conservation Corps, along with another nearby site along the Navasota River. A replica fort was built on the fort site, while a 670 acre lake was built on the river, together with camping and outdoor recreational facilities. Both sites took the name Fort Parker, both were operated after being built by Texas Parks and Wildlife Department, and for a time they were complexed together for more efficient operation by the department. Over time, locals began referring to the fort site as Old Fort Parker, and the lake site as Fort Parker State Park. The replica fort at the Old Fort site was rebuilt in 1967. Today, the Old Fort is operated jointly by the nearby cities of Groesbeck, Mexia, and Limestone County. Fort Parker State Park continues to operate as a Texas Parks and Wildlife Department site. Because of the close connection between both Fort Parkers, there is a limited amount of Fort Parker State Park materials within this collection. Several pictures from a third local historic site, the Confederate Reunion Grounds State Historic Site, can also be found in this collection.
Scope and Content
The Parker Family-Fort Parker collection begins with 1823 copies of legal papers on the Parker family, and goes until 1983 with a book on Quanah Parker. The bulk of the collection is between 1935 and 1965, with a large amount of essays and other printed materials undated. The largest series is literary productions.
The Parker Family-Fort Parker collection was assembled by Ernest Connally for his personal research. His research centered on the Fort Parker story, and included famous Texas figures Cynthia Ann Parker and Quanah Parker, the last major Comanche chief to give up warfare against the United States. The collection contains many printed materials, correspondence, and rare early photographs of the Mexia, Texas, area.
Arrangement
The Parker Family-Fort Parker collection was organized with folder labels, but these labels did not always accurately reflect the contents of the folders. No previous finding aid or inventory was available.
The collection is arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, II. Legal Documents, III. Literary Productions, IV. Photographic Materials, and V. Artifacts.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2581. Acquired 1984-08-20
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Parker-Anglin Family collection, Inclusive: 1860-1917, undated, Bulk: 1860-1885
Quanah Parker Family papers, Bulk: 1952-1965, undated, Inclusive: 1933-1987, undated
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Parker, Cynthia Ann, 1827?-1864.; Parker, Quanah, 1854?-1911.
Subjects (Organizations)
Fort Parker State Park (Tex.)
Places
Limestone County (Tex.) -- History.; Old Fort Parker State Historical Park (Tex.); Parker's Fort (Tex.); Texas -- Photographs.
Subjects
Comanche Indians -- History.; Frontier and pioneer life -- Texas.; Historic sites -- Texas -- Limestone County.; Indian captivities -- Texas.; Massacres -- Texas -- Fort Parker.; Postcards.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Essays.; Legal documents.; Pamphlets.; Research notes.
- Correspondence, 1934-1975, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Unknown.
  Biography/Profile
  Series includes letters about the grand opening of Old Fort Parker and Fort Parker State Parks as state parks for the local community. Correspondence also includes answers to Connally’s questions about Quanah Parker’s wives and children, the physical status of the Old Fort through the years, and other matters pertaining to Old Fort Parker. The series is in good to excellent condition.
  - Correspondence, 1934-1936 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1936 May 19-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1962 June (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, July-1962 August 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1962 August 15-18 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1962 August 20-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Postcards: General, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Postcards: Old Fort Parker, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Postcards: Fort Parker State Park, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Legal Documents, 1823-1957; 2
  Series includes legal documents pertaining to the Parker family and the reburial of Cynthia Ann Parker in 1956-1957. The series is in good to excellent condition.
  - General: Copies (1 of 2), 1823-1836 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General: Copies (2 of 2), 1823-1836 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cynthia Ann Parker Reburial, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Literary Productions, 1891-1983, undated; 3
  - General, 1919-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Programs: General, 1941-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Programs: “The Fall of Fort Parker” (Old Fort Parker), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook: Parker Family, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Essays: General, 1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Essays: Old Fort Parker, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Essays: [Capture of Cynthia Ann Parker] (1 of 2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Essays: [Capture of Cynthia Ann Parker] (2 of 2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Essays: “Illinois Days of Daniel Parker, Texas Colonizer”, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Essays: “Tales of the Waco Indians”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Essays: Texas Indians, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Essays: “The Fort Parker Massacre and It’s Aftermath”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Printed Materials: Parker Letters at U.S. Army Museum, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Printed Materials: “Descendants of Quanah Parker” (1 of 2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Printed Materials: “Descendants of Quanah Parker” (2 of 2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Pamphlets: Old Fort Parker, 1935- 1955 undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Book: Cynthia Ann Parker: The Story of Her Capture, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Book: Guide to Texas Indians (1 of 3), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Book: Guide to Texas Indians (2 of 3), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Book: Guide to Texas Indians (3 of 3), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Book: Quanah: The Serpent Eagle, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Book: Texas Indian Lore, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Book: The Karankawa Indians, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Notes: Biographies, Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Notes: Parker Family Genealogy (1 of 4), Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notes: Parker Family Genealogy (2 of 4), Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notes: Parker Family Genealogy (3 of 4), Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notes: Parker Family Genealogy (4 of 4), Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notes: Personal, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notes: Quanah Parker, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Notes: Texas Indians (1 of 4), Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notes: Texas Indians (2 of 4), Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Notes: Texas Indians (3 of 4), Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Notes: Texas Indians (4 of 4), Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Notes: Outlines (1 of 2), Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Notes: Outlines (2 of 2), Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Clippings: General, 1941-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Clippings: American Indians, 1955-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clippings: American Indians (1 of 2), Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Clippings: American Indians (2 of 2), Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Clippings: Old Fort Parker, 1953-1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Clippings: Parker Family, 1937-1962 August (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Clippings: Parker Family, 1962 December-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Photographic Materials, undated; 4
  Series includes a large number of excellent photographs around the Mexia area, emphasizing Old Fort Parker, Fort Parker State Park, and the Confederate Reunion Grounds State Historic Site. Of particular interest are the aerial pictures of Fort Parker State Park, perhaps taken during the 1940s, that show outlines of the major buildings, roads, and cleared and forested areas. Other photographs include general pictures of American Indians and copies of historic pictures of Quanah Parker and his family. The series is in average to excellent condition.
  - Photographs: General (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Photographs: General (2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Photographs: American Indians: General (1 of 5), undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Photographs: American Indians: General (2 of 5), undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Photographs: American Indians: General (3 of 5), undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Photographs: American Indians: General (4 of 5), undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Photographs: American Indians: General (5 of 5), undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Photographs: Mexia Area (1 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Photographs: Mexia Area (2 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Photographs: Mexia Area (3 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Photographs: Mexia Area: Aerial Views (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Photographs: Mexia Area: Aerial Views (2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Photographs: Old Fort Parker (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Photographs: Old Fort Parker: (2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Photographs: Old Fort Parker: Artwork, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Photographs: Old Fort Parker: Event, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Photographs: Fort Parker Cemetery, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Photographs: Cynthia Ann Parker, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Photographs: Quanah Parker and Family (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Photographs: Quanah Parker and Family (2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Photographs: Parker Family Reunions, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Negatives: Mexia Area: Aerial Views, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Negatives: Old Fort Parker, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Negatives: Mexia Area, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Negatives: Quanah Parker and Family, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Artifacts, 1936; 5
  Series includes one wooden Centennial nickel. This square-shaped piece of wood was given out by the Mexia and Groesbeck Chambers of Commerce during the 1936 Centennial, and was used as a kind of currency during the festivities. The series is in excellent condition.
  - Artifacts: Centennial Nickel, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 45)